export const MANAGEMENTINLIVINGA2023 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Occurrences in the family that are not planned for but need attention are termed as",
A: "epidemics.",
B: "crisis.",
C: "events.",
D: "happenings.",
answer: "B. crisis.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Management is a process which involves",
A: "planning, budgeting and implementing.",
B: "planning, implementing and evaluation.",
C: "planning, organizing and implementing.",
D: "planning, organizing and adjusting.",
answer: "B. planning, implementing and evaluation.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. How we think and feel about our body is our",
A: "sexual identity.",
B: "body image.",
C: "sexuality.",
D: "genetics.",
answer: "B. body image.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Thrush, rapid weight loss and persistent diarrhoea are some symptoms of",
A: "hepatitis B.",
B: "cholera.",
C: "stomach ulcer.",
D: "HIV/AIDS.",
answer: "D. HIV/AIDS.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The most likely outcome of adolescent promiscuity is",
A: "delayed marriage.",
B: "sexually transmitted disease.",
C: "rejection by the society.",
D: "early pregnancy.",
answer: "D. early pregnancy.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Feeling of guilt, bruising of the genital organs, pre-mature ejaculation are",
A: "effects of premarital sex.",
B: "effects of sex abuse.",
C: "consequences of masturbation.",
D: "consequences of rape.",
answer: "C. consequences of masturbation.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Hand washing prevents diseases like",
A: "cholera.",
B: "malaria.",
C: "hay fever.",
D: "meningitis.",
answer: "A. cholera.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. A boy started using cocaine because he wanted to feel the effect of it. This means the boy abused the drug through",
A: "frustration.",
B: "peer influence.",
C: "curiosity.",
D: "school influence.",
answer: "C. curiosity.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Cannabis is used by adolescents mainly to",
A: "stimulate themselves.",
B: "enhance mental efficiency.",
C: "enable them misbehave.",
D: "have self-control.",
answer: "A. stimulate themselves.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Testate succession means sharing a deceased person’s property according to",
A: "customary law.",
B: "one’s will.",
C: "civil law.",
D: "family wishes.",
answer: "B. one’s will.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The stage of the family life cycle where a couple makes adjustments in order to maintain their marriage is the",
A: "beginning stage.",
B: "expanding stage.",
C: "contracting stage.",
D: "empty nest stage.",
answer: "D. empty nest stage.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The blessing of a marriage by the church",
A: "may not have any legal support.",
B: "gives the man authority.",
C: "gives the woman security.",
D: "has the same status as ordinance marriage.",
answer: "A. may not have any legal support.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. A challenge that does not require adjustment by the family is",
A: "personality clash.",
B: "financial problems.",
C: "truancy.",
D: "communication.",
answer: "D. communication.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. Which of the following is most likely to break husband-wife relationship?",
A: "Lack of financial support",
B: "Lack of affection",
C: "Lack of sex",
D: "Lack of co-operation",
answer: "B. Lack of affection",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. A permanent birth control method for females is",
A: "apill.",
B: "an intra-uterine device.",
C: "femidom.",
D: "tubal ligation.",
answer: "D. tubal ligation.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Communication skills include",
A: "participation.",
B: "listening.",
C: "hearing.",
D: "evaluating.",
answer: "B. listening.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Expressing feelings and sharing ideas with other people are forms of",
A: "publication.",
B: "communication.",
C: "advertising.",
D: "presentation.",
answer: "B. communication.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. In order to restore the muscle tone of one’s figure after childbirth, the mother should",
A: "eat balanced diet.",
B: "wear waist trainers.",
C: "exercise regularly.",
D: "attend post-natal clinic.",
answer: "C. exercise regularly.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The following constitute the female reproductive system,",
A: "ovaries, breast, uterus and fallopian tube.",
B: "urethra, vagina, uterus and fallopian tube.",
C: "stomach, vagina, uterus and ovaries.",
D: "ovaries, fallopian tube, uterus and vagina.",
answer: "D. ovaries, fallopian tube, uterus and vagina.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Emotional abuse of a child includes",
A: "being rejected.",
B: "selling the child.",
C: "merciless beating.",
D: "denial of food.",
answer: "A. being rejected.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. A home which is not likely to produce a drug addict is",
A: "a broken home.",
B: "an authoritarian home.",
C: "a single-parent home.",
D: "an authoritative home.",
answer: "D. an authoritative home.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The most serious problem in pregnancy is",
A: "pre-eclampsia.",
B: "vomiting.",
C: "frequent urination.",
D: "heartburn.",
answer: "A. pre-eclampsia.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The decision and activities that make families and individuals achieve the kind of life they want is known as",
A: "standards.",
B: "values.",
C: "management.",
D: "goals.",
answer: "C. management.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. If you place high value on education, your goal is to",
A: "study very hard.",
B: "access the internet.",
C: "visit the library.",
D: "buy more books.",
answer: "A. study very hard.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. A home maker who is able to predict consequences of actions taken",
A: "has consideration.",
B: "is tolerant.",
C: "is creative.",
D: "has foresight.",
answer: "D. has foresight.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. If one is unable to have a clear life goal, the need that may never be achieved is",
A: "self-esteem need.",
B: "social need.",
C: "security need.",
D: "physiological need.",
answer: "A. self-esteem need.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Which of the following in decision making is also called major decision?",
A: "Satellite decision",
B: "Central decision",
C: "Chain decision",
D: "Majority decision",
answer: "B. Central decision",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. One activity at the planning stage of management is",
A: "standard setting.",
B: "controlling performance.",
C: "checking standards.",
D: "assessing performance.",
answer: "A. standard setting.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Management in living covers a wide area of study because",
A: "individual and family needs are many.",
B: "resources are difficult to access.",
C: "of the varied nature of the resources of individuals and families.",
D: "of the varied nature of the needs of individuals and families.",
answer: "D. of the varied nature of the needs of individuals and families.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Time spent on income generating activities is referred to as",
A: "biological time.",
B: "work time.",
C: "clock time.",
D: "non-work time.",
answer: "B. work time.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. A motivator that mostly affects a person’s feelings is",
A: "events.",
B: "values.",
C: "goals.",
D: "standards.",
answer: "B. values.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. To be successful in managing resources, one should",
A: "be able to recognize the resources.",
B: "accept that resources are scarce.",
C: "give direction for the use of resources.",
D: "prioritize the use of resources.",
answer: "D. prioritize the use of resources.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. One needs to plan the use of time because",
A: "it can be accumulated.",
B: "time past can be retrieved.",
C: "time past cannot be brought back.",
D: "it is in equal proportion for all.",
answer: "C. time past cannot be brought back.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Dovetailing tasks means",
A: "arranging tasks in a sequential manner.",
B: "putting rhythm in activities.",
C: "doing two or more tasks at the same time.",
D: "allocating time to two or more activities within a period.",
answer: "C. doing two or more tasks at the same time.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. For every physical work, the basic resources required are",
A: "money and energy.",
B: "time and energy.",
C: "experience and skills.",
D: "creativity and skills.",
answer: "B. time and energy.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Mental fatigue occurs as a result of",
A: "frustration, lack of interest, lack of energy and boredom.",
B: "lack of energy, boredom, lack of exercise and frustration.",
C: "boredom, nervous tension, lack of interest and energy.",
D: "boredom, frustration, lack of interest and nervous tension.",
answer: "D. boredom, frustration, lack of interest and nervous tension.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. A housewife can save time by",
A: "writing down all the work to be done.",
B: "starting housework early.",
C: "carefully planning the work to be done.",
D: "setting out rest periods in-between tasks.",
answer: "C. carefully planning the work to be done.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Essential and basic things people must have in order to survive are",
A: "values.",
B: "needs.",
C: "standards.",
D: "wants.",
answer: "B. needs.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Mortgage loan is used to",
A: "secure valuable property.",
B: "finance an agricultural project.",
C: "finance a housing project.",
D: "fund tertiary education.",
answer: "C. finance a housing project.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. A tenant needs to",
A: "keep the house clean.",
B: "repair structural faults.",
C: "maintain fixtures.",
D: "paint external walls.",
answer: "A. keep the house clean.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Housing regulations that prevent overcrowding in an area are referred to as",
A: "zoning ordinance.",
B: "housing codes.",
C: "aesthetic regulations.",
D: "building restrictions.",
answer: "A. zoning ordinance.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Home owners are required by law to pay",
A: "property tax.",
B: "property insurance.",
C: "home ownership insurance.",
D: "value added tax.",
answer: "A. property tax.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. When textures are used to suggest formality, they have",
A: "psychological effect on people.",
B: "social effect on people.",
C: "emotional effect on people.",
D: "physiological effect on people.",
answer: "A. psychological effect on people.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. A shade and tone combine well with",
A: "blue.",
B: "yellow.",
C: "red.",
D: "white.",
answer: "D. white.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Warm colours on a wall make a room.seem",
A: "narrower.",
B: "smaller.",
C: "bigger.",
D: "longer.",
answer: "C. bigger.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. When scrubbing a concrete floor,",
A: "scrub small area at a time and wipe.",
B: "wet the whole floor to.loosen dirt.",
C: "scrub according to the grain.",
D: "rinse with water and wipe.",
answer: "A. scrub small area at a time and wipe.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The cost of electricity depends on wattage and",
A: "length of time used.",
B: "size of appliance.",
C: "brand of appliance",
D: "design of appliance.",
answer: "A. length of time used.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following best describes terrazzo floors?",
A: "Hard wearing, needs resurfacing and may absorb water",
B: "Attractive, may absorb water and.easy to maintain",
C: "Attractive, hard wearing and easy to'maintain",
D: "Attractive, can indent and easy to clean",
answer: "C. Attractive, hard wearing and easy to'maintain",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Overheating occurs in a circuit if",
A: "live and earth wires touch.",
B: "neutral and earth wires touch.",
C: "live and neutral wires touch.",
D: "neuiral and negative wires touch.",
answer: "C. live and neutral wires touch.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Hard water contains",
A: "calcium tetraoxosulphate.",
B: "magnesium sulphate.",
C: "sodiuin hydroxide.",
D: "aluminium sulphate.",
answer: "B. magnesium sulphate.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question51",
question:  "51. A standing order is",
A: "a bill paid regularly on behalf of a customer.",
B: "a deduction for services rendered to a customer.",
C: "an interest on a fixed deposit.",
D: "a yield on investment made.",
answer: "A. a bill paid regularly on behalf of a customer.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question52",
question:  "52. The regular contribution made to an insurance company is termed as",
A: "policy.",
B: "investment.",
C: "premium.",
D: "savings.",
answer: "C. premium.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question53",
question:  "53. Social security scheme allows a contributor to",
A: "withdraw a fixed amount of money from the scheme every month.",
B: "enjoy benefits only after retirement.",
C: "make partial withdrawal from investment.",
D: "make 5% contribution to the scheme every month.",
answer: "B. enjoy benefits only after retirement.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question54",
question:  "54. Family members sewing for the family is an example of",
A: "household service income.",
B: "household production income.",
C: "household savings income.",
D: "fringe benefit income.",
answer: "B. household production income.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question55",
question:  "55. An example of an insurance scheme is",
A: "stocks.",
B: "bonds.",
C: "ied endowment.",
D: "shares.",
answer: "C. lied endowment.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question56",
question:  "56. When an individual uses electricity and pays for it latet, the one is using",
A: "instalment credit.",
B: "sales credit.",
C: "consumer credit.",
D: "service credit.",
answer: "C. consumer credit.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question57",
question:  "57. The most reliable method of payment of school fees is by using",
A: "banker’s draft.",
B: "open cheque.",
C: "postal order.",
D: "crossed cheques.",
answer: "A. banker’s draft.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question58",
question:  "58. People who buy goods in bulk from producers and sell to consumers are called",
A: "storekeepers.",
B: "agents.",
C: "wholesalers.",
D: "retailers.",
answer: "C. wholesalers.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question59",
question:  "59. Basic documents used for buying and selling include",
A: "collateral, receipt and invoice.",
B: "receipt, invoice and cheque.",
C: "invoice, cheque and waybill.",
D: "receipt, invoice and waybill.",
answer: "B. receipt, invoice and cheque.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question60",
question:  "60. Labour market involves the supply of and demand for",
A: "consumer goods and services.",
B: "skills and knowledge.",
C: "services and creativity.",
D: "money and assets.",
answer: "B. skills and knowledge.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]